Good evening. Thank you so much for
coming. My name is Ma Hinch and I'm the
executive director at the East Central
Intergovernmental Association. It's a
mouthful, isn't it? EPIA. So, we're a
council of governments that supports uh
Clinton, Cedar, Delaware, Debuke, and
Jackson counties. And so, um we're here
tonight, I think, for all all of us are
here for the same reason. We want what's
best for Cascade, right? is a community
that we care about and we love about
that we love and maybe we have different
ideas about what is best for Cascade.
But if we can start from the from the
heart of that that we want what's best
for our community then I think that
we'll have a really great discussion.
This is an opportunity for you to learn
about the specific project that's being
proposed here in Cascade and some time
to answer but to ask questions and have
them be answered. So, um I think we
probably have had enough because I see
some still on the table that we have an
agenda for you this evening. There's
some basic ground rules on that agenda
that we want we really want this to to
be a productive conversation and to be
focused on the project here that that
pretty soon you're going to hear about
from these two gentlemen. Um they're
they have obviously a slideshow and
they're going to show you and kind of
talk through the project afterwards. We
will make sure that we have some time
for questions and answers. So when we
get to that point, I'll remind you again
of the ground rules before we get into
the questions and answers. We will wait
until they're done presenting to do
questions. And so we're going to let
them kind of get into the flow of the
discussion and then we'll let we'll give
you that time before they get started. A
few house housekeeping things. Restrooms
are in the back corner over here. Um we
are recording the presentation tonight.
For those that can't be here, it will be
posted on the Cascade the City of
Cascades Facebook page. So, if you have
friends or family that um wanted to be
here tonight could not, please know that
it will be available for them as well.
Um and I think with that we'll probably
get started. So, I'm going to introduce
our two speakers. So, first we have Adam
Kings and he's the CEO of Simple Mining.
Um Adam just Adam and his wife just had
a baby so we were all going baby
pictures before we get started here. Um,
so that's what we were doing up here.
And then we also have Jeremy Richard,
who I don't believe just had a baby with
his wife, but Jeremy, the CEO of Monro
Valley um electric cooperative. So um
both of these gentlemen are going to
describe the project that is being
proposed and then
>> All right. Good evening everyone. Thank
you for u taking time to come here and
visit and you know learn more about the
project that we're proposing in Cascade.
Um
thank you. Um so we there was an online
submission for questions and I took a
look at every single question that was
submitted and this presentation here
tonight is meant to you know cover every
single question that was submitted. So
appreciate all of those questions and um
if for whatever reason we don't get to
your question tonight um my contact
information is there. send me an email
happy to get back to you have a call you
know and answer any questions that you
might have. So the questions that we um
had you know collectively were around
these different categories. You know
what what are we even proposing here? Um
what is the the water situation, the
cooling situation look like? How many
jobs? Where is the site? Um noise
levels, what are the benefits to
Cascade? Um questions around energy
usage, um safety, environmental health
concerns, and then zoning
accountability. So, we plan on
addressing all of those different
concerns here tonight. Again, if we
don't get to one of your specific
questions, please feel free to reach out
and contact me anytime. Um, want to
start with just a little bit about who
we are and um how we how we got started
in business. Uh, a little bit of
background. I'm not much of a guy to
talk about myself, but I think it'll be,
you know, good to to know a little bit
more about me. Um, so I was uh uh went
to high school in St. cancer. Uh little
small town right on the Iowa Minnesota
border. Went down to school and to
University of Northern Iowa. Um didn't
know what I wanted to do. Um ended up
dropping out and opening my first
business which was a cell phone repair
business. So opened that back in 2017.
Um it's called QuickFix and then it
recently rebranded to CPR cell phone
repair. So we have a location over in
Debuke that maybe some of you have had
your thumbs fixed there. to do it
perfectly. We did a good job and
everybody's happy. So, um, this company,
uh, Simple Mining started in 2021. Um,
we were running the software bear
stores. Uh, things were a little crazy
with COVID and we started running some
computers in the back of our cell bear
business and, um, that's kind of how the
simple mining company got started. So,
um, originally this project began as a
Bitcoin mining proposal. Um to make it
really really simple, Bitcoin miners are
just computers. Um we build the
infrastructure to help those computers
run. And what our proposal is going to
be here today, which we're going to get
into, is you know more of a traditional
data center, but the same core
principles apply. We're building
infrastructure to run computers. Um so
that's uh Holly, if you don't mind. Yes.
So that's a little bit more about um how
we started. It was a modular facility.
Um, and then this proposal now is for a
more of a traditional data center inside
of a permanent building, not the modular
um, type of infrastructure that we use
on the Bitcoin side of things. Um, why
this matters, data centers are already a
part of our daily lives and this is
really important technology for, you
know, the future. Um, all of these are
just different examples of how we use
data centers every single day, maybe
without even realizing it. Um but
there's very very important you know um
things that we use in our daily lives
that maybe we don't immediately think
about that are all of those things are
routed through a data center and it's
very critically important you know such
things as iCloud photos everybody here
I'm sure has you know or most people
probably have an iPhone and they have
those you know photos backed up in the
cloud I'm sure I would you just talked
about my baby that was recently born
I've got all those pictures backed up
and if something happened to those I'd
be devastated right Um that's just one
important way. Obviously, hospitals,
government services, there's other
critically important, you know, reasons
on why we need data centers. Um and the
the the growth is going to continue in
data centers as these applications um
continue to expand. So this is the site.
Um this is a conceptional plan that we
worked with our engineering firm on. Um
it it'll change, you know, slightly, but
I think that this is a pretty good
overview of, you know, what the proposal
is going to look like. Um we have a
building that's centered in the
property. Um we have about you know 216
to 291 feet of setbacks from each
property line. We really focused on
centering the building and the the
center of the property that we have. Um
you can see the various um the street is
on the side. We have the substation for
the um utility in the bottom portion.
The electrical and cooling yard and then
we have some screening on the far east
side of the property. So, uh, this
particular site does not need a storm
water retention basin as there's a
regional basin kind of across the
street. So, preliminary site layout, but
this is, um, I think overall a pretty
pretty good overview of what this
particular facility is going to look
like. This is a standard, you know,
either pre-engineered or pre-cast
concrete building, you know, very
similar to a lot of the different
buildings that you would see out in an
industrial park um, in this area.
um just to get a sense of scale for this
particular project because data center
is a very very broad broad term and I
think it's really important to focus in
on the facts of what we're specifically
proposing here at this location. Um
because you hear about these you know
just huge huge huge mega sites that are
thousands of acres and you know
gigawatts of power and hard to even
comprehend. Um just as a comparison um
there's a lot of activity going on in
Cedar Rapids. I'm sure everybody's you
know heard about that. Um the the
combined QTS and Google campuses in
Cedar Rapids are about,026
acres. Um this particular project is
15.2 gross acreage. Um and our building
is about 60,000 square ft. Um so very,
you know, standard building size that
you would find any other business, you
know, in Cape with that particular size
facility. Um so much larger land
requirements for those other facilities.
This would be considered a very very
very small data center just for clarity
and you can see that with the the power
as well. So the power in the two-seater
rapids campuses is about 1.65 gawatts or
1,650 megawatts. This particular project
is roughly 40. So wanted to just give a
little bit of a sense of scale.
Another really common question that we
get asked is about the the cooling
technology and the water usage. What
we're proposing here is a closed loop
hydrocooling facility. So the water that
we would use at this particular facility
would be limited to just facilities for
our employees. Um think restroom, sink,
you know, other you know maintenance
type of items but we would not be using
any water for cooling of the facility.
Uh this is an illustration here that
kind of shows how you know the liquid
goes through the the computer. um it you
know it warms up as it's cooling the
computer down that goes um through a um
air cooled condenser and then cools that
fluid back down and then it just
recirculates and um you know we'll talk
more about this during the presentation
but this is a um a very common type of
system that lots of businesses use for
cooling. Um there's no visible plume.
It's just a warm air that's that's the
byproduct of this particular solution.
And um this is a liquid that we bring in
that is very long lasting liquid. You
know, 10 10 plus years. Um we have a
10ear warranty through our vendors on
this particular liquid. So we're not
constantly taking this liquid out. Um if
we in the future did have to remove this
liquid, it would be removed and you know
properly disposed of and recycled. It's
not going to be you know dumped down the
drain for example. So um noise noise is
another very very common question that
we get um that we get asked and and and
we are in alignment on this particular
situation. We're focused on locating
this in the industrial park where it's
zoned you know heavy industrial for this
particular location. Um we are very open
to clear limits you know um you know
very easy enforceable clear guidelines.
Um but this closed loop cooling
technology is is overall it's a very
quiet um a lot of the you know the noise
concerns that you might hear about are
related to air cool technology where the
um cooling fans are very very you know
fast RPMs and very very frequency. Um
this cooling technology is is very very
quiet. It's a um you know it's kind of a
low hum. Um and we have a facility that
you open to showing anybody anytime. We
It's just down the road in Manchester.
It's about 50 megawatts, so it's larger
than this facility that we're proposing
here in Cat State. And um that
facility's been operating for a year
now. And we've had zero complaints. So
that's located in the Manchester
Industrial Park. And um again, happy to,
you know, show anybody around there just
to just to see what this type of
technology looks like, feels like,
sounds like, all those sorts of things.
So, um, we're we're not here to say that
we don't make any sound, but it's very
very minimal overall, and we're
certainly aligned with making sure that
we're going to be good neighbors with
clear and enforcable limits. So, just to
talk about the, you know, noise. Um, the
normal conversation is 60 dibels. Um,
you know, typical ordinance limits are
around 65. Um, our headquarters is in
Cedar Falls, so the ordinance limit
there is 65. Um, vacuum cleaners are
very loud. The hydro cooling
infrastructure is around 50. Um so it's
it's pretty pretty moderate on the um on
the noise levels.
So safety environments and health um so
we are going to build to code um you
know we're going to have permits we're
going to be monitored um we will have
backup generation. Uh this is only for
backup scenarios if there's a power
outage. Um it's tested periodically and
it's operated under a state air per uh
air permit. Um so very strict guidelines
there for what we can and cannot do. Um
health the main concerns there you know
kind of the noise and the generators. So
we address both of those batteries and
fire suppression built to code. We'll
work with the local you know emergency
uh departments and the fire department
to establish an emergency action plan
and and those sorts of things. Um
utility outages we we would um operate
on you know battery and generators. So
that's um you know that would not you
know affect our facility. and then storm
water is going to drain to the regional
basin. Um and then you know that was
confirmed that we would not need a
retention pond for this facility. And
then um the electronic waste we would
handle you know according to the
federal, state and local rules. So um
the last thing that's a very very
important point is we are designing this
to a lead standard. Lead is the the US's
um green building rating system. It's a
very very strict rating system that
actually goes all the way through the
initial design through construction and
how the building operates. So it's very
strict parameters to ensure that um you
know things are built efficiently and
and and you know uh different different
things are handled in a in a proper
manner. Um so it's a very um high
standard of building and operation and
designs that we are um planning to
design for. So jobs that's another
question that we get we get asked. Um
this particular location we would be
anticipating around 20 to 24 20 to 25
full-time jobs. Um some of those jobs
would be around operations um site
management, maintenance, electrical and
mechanical uh security and then IT
staff. Um these particular positions we
would um have an average of around 75 to
$80,000 of salary. um with full medical
benefits, pay a time off, 401k, you
know, we like to, you know, make sure
that we can attract, you know, and
retain great local talent. So, um we
intend to hire locally working with NICC
and any other local partners to develop
local talent. Um for example, we've had
um some pretty good success working with
Buckeye Community College in in Waterl
for our facilities there. Uh we've got
about 40 employees in Cedar Falls and um
yeah like to make sure that we can have
pretty competitive pay to this facility
is a 247 365 operation so we have to
have local talent to be able to run this
facility.
Uh and with that I will turn it over to
Jeremy to talk on the energy side of
things. I'll come back in.
Good evening once again. My name is
Jeremy Richards and I'm the CEO at
Makoka Valley Electric Cooperative. I'm
sure we have a few Makoka Valley members
in the audience here, but for those that
are not familiar, um we provide electric
service to approximately 18,000 meters.
Um located in Jones, Jackson, Delaware,
and Debuke counties. And then uh as of
about 10 years ago, we also got into the
uh fiber broadband internet business.
and we uh currently have about 8,500
internet subscribers. So, kind of gives
you an idea of who we are.
So, tonight uh based on the questions
that were entered
for us to answer, I kind of divided them
into four four themes or four different
groupings that we're going to cover and
you can see those on the slide up here.
Um I don't have any additional slides,
so I'm just going to talk through it and
answer any questions that you may have
later. Our first question that was
listed a few times was what's the
relationship between Maka Valley
Electric Cooperative and Simple Mining
and it's it's very simple. Um Simple
Mining is a member of Moka Valley um
currently based on the site that Adam
mentioned in management. So they do have
a service with us. Um, and then here
they're looking obviously at this
potential project in Cascade. But they
are a member, no different than any
house, any new business, any grain
drying facility. Um, they are a member
of us and we will, you know, within our
service territory.
Um,
for this particular site, uh, Adam
mentioned that it has started as
potentially a Bitcoin site. We had a lot
of conversation with his team at that
time again trying to figure out what the
energy requirements would be. Um how we
could serve that load, how the system
could handle that load. And then more
recently it has transition to a data
center conversation which from a load
perspective and a system impact on the
power grid is very similar. It doesn't
really differentiate that much if it's a
big coin or a data center. But as of
today, we currently do not have
agreements in place with them to move
forward. And as I mentioned, we we just
recently started the data center side of
it, which has some a little different
requirements that we'll work through um
or attempt to work through. But uh so
we've had lots of discussion, but as of
currently, no contracts have been
executed and signed. Um, one other
common question I get, I believe a few
people from CAS data called in and asked
this question, is is the co-op required
to serve a data center or can you just
say no? Um, and the short answer is yes,
we are required to make an effort to
serve the data center. Um, the state of
Iowa has electric service territory laws
that define geographic regions are
applied to each utility all across the
state. So if they're in our territory,
we're required to make a good faith
effort to serve that load. Uh the thing
to keep in mind is that doesn't mean
that serving that load has to be at the
expense of the cooperative or the rest
of the members. Uh but again, you do
have to make a good faith effort to to
be able to serve that load. So that's
kind of the summary of the relationship
between the Focal and Simple Mining. Um
next I'm going to get into you know
what's the impact on the system capacity
for the power grid and uh as Adam
mentioned earlier this site is projected
to be around 40 megawatts um and again
whether it's Bitcoin or data center that
40 megawws is the peak that we had you
know been discussing and and working
towards and uh we completed a capacity
study central Iowa power cooperative is
our transmission and generation provider
so we worked in conjunction with them to
analyze the power supply transmission in
this region and uh determined if you
know what we could serve given the goal
of around 40 megawatts and uh so we
found that the transmission is adequate
in this area to serve that size of load
but another thing I want to point out
again a common question we get is we
make sure our practice s practice is
that if we have a 40 megawatt load we're
not taking all of incurred extra
capacity. So we set aside a portion of
the existing capacity for future native
load growth um so that you know the city
of Cascade this area this region can
continue to grow because we don't want
to use all of the existing capacity for
native growth for one large load. So
that's an approach we take across our
system. Um that's the approach CICO
takes with us and then CICO also serves
13 other co-ops in 50 counties across
Iowa. So that's that's basically the
approach across the state for for
electric crops that are part of SIP
codees
that one pretty good. So the next group
would be who pays for upgrades and again
simple mining this is pretty simple if
we treat them like if you're building a
new service for a house you were
building a new service for a business
you pay for the cost up front. So,
Simple Mining would pay 100% of all
upgrades to serve this new load in this
area. That includes transmission costs,
substation costs, and distribution
system costs. And we require payment
upfront before we will order a single
hold. And then once the process is over,
there's a true up. You know, if they owe
additional, they would pay us
additional. If we had collected too much
upfront, we would reimburse that amount.
But it's all handled up front so that we
make sure that the costs are covered
before we get started.
For this side of load, for this size of
load, we would also require simple to
bring new generation. I had talked about
the capacity. Um so if we need new
generation, which we would um we want to
make sure that the data centers aren't
consuming the generation currently in
place for native load or existing users.
So that is a approach you hear by a lot
of utilities across the Midwest across
the country is you know data centers
large loads they don't have to be data
centers but large loads need to supply
their own generation so that we don't
run you know getting closer to running
out due to native growth so that's a big
piece of it um obviously the building
the transmission line you know that all
makes sense but I want to make sure that
everyone understands the generation is
tied to that as
And then the last kind of category here
is what's the impact on rates? And if
it's handled properly, a large load
should have neutral or positive impact
on rates. Um it's kind of up to how
every utility would handle it. But uh
overall it should provide would provide
rate stability for our entire co-op.
It's a steady revenue stream. Um it
helps with cash flows. you look at the
the utility co-op, we have a bunch of a
large amount of fixed cost. It's spread
over a much larger kilowatt hour pool
which helps balance some of those costs
out. So, um again, net neutral, net
positive on terms of impact on rates,
but I want to also point out that
doesn't mean there's not going to be a
rate increase. We had a rate increase
last April that was not tied to a data
center. We're going to have a rate
increase in the future that's not going
to be tied to a data center. And the key
thing that I want to hopefully make sure
everybody understands is paying their
way up from paying their way as they go
um should not increase the rest of our
members rates.
So that's kind of areas that were
electric related and we'll have some
time for questions here in a minute but
I'll turn it back over to
>> thanks Jeremy. Um just going to benefits
to Cascade. This is going to be a
material investment. Um this particular
investment we're looking will be around
400 million um total investment in
Cascade. So it's a material investment
um you know with material new taxable
value. Uh work for area businesses. We
intend on using local contractors and
Iowa suppliers in every aspect that we
can to build this particular facility.
Um we did that locally in Manchester. We
work with local contractors there. Um
Jeremy touched on the, you know, the
cost shift for the um for the utility
side of things. Um local jobs, same
thing. Mentioned that already. Um
operations, maintenance, you know, we
intend to hire locally. Wages that are
staying local and really hard. We'll
touch on this on on the next slide, but
we want to be involved and we want to
support um you know, this is this is
something that's really important to me.
Um if you don't mind the slide yet. Um
so so zoning accountability. So so what
we're looking for is you know the city
will set rules that are you know um
just very clear and concise rules and we
can operate with them that are losing
the mic here um that are enforceable
where you know all of these concerns are
addressed and um you know it just gives
a very clear set of conditions where we
can operate. we would not build this
facility if we were going to be
violating, you know, the the ordinance
that would be established for this
particular facility. We would, you know,
want to make sure that we're abiding and
and following those clear and concise
rules. Um and um yeah, we want to be a
good long-term partner like we are in
all of the other communities that we
operate in across Iowa lead.
So, this is how we be good neighbors. um
clear noise limits towards um you know
enforcable limits and and we'll need
them um and and you know we wouldn't
build the facility if we were going to
exceed any you know noise ordinance
limitations um closed loop cooling so
minimal water use this is just enough
water and and we're fine with the cap on
water use we we are not going to use
millions and millions of gallons of
water a day that um that is not the
design that particular design you you've
maybe seen seen or heard about where
data centers are using millions of
gallons of water a day. Um what that is
is an evaporative cooling system where
uh it's it's an open loop and it what it
does is it allows for a little bit
better PU the peak um usage
effectiveness. What that means is um
it's just a little bit more cost
effective to actually cool all of the
infrastructure with an openloop system
that uses water directly from the city
as an example. um that is not what we're
proposing here. We're proposing a closed
loop system. I think that has a much
better overall solution. Um even if it's
a little bit less efficient from a
cooling perspective. Um so that's our
proposal there. Um well screened site.
We're committed to this being a very
attractive. It's a significant
investment and we want to make sure that
this is an attractive site that's you
know screened with an augur fence or you
know any other fencing that we might
need. um and that it's a it's a nice
looking facility. We want to we want to
be proud of the way that this looks. So,
it will work well within the you know um
if there's a data center ordinance
that's established, we'll work within
those parameters. We would not build
this facility and make this investment
if we were not able to follow the rules
and risk any you know potential issues
with our investment. Um
um so this is just a you know want to
touch on you know some ways that we've
been in the community and you know
growing up in small town I was saying
this again touched about um you know
being involved in lots of different you
know sports and those types of things. I
was very fortunate there's a few
different companies that did lots of
sponsorships for uniforms and travel for
different you know sporting events and
those types of things. Um so so we want
to be involved in the community. We want
to give back. Um, you know, these are
just a few different ways that we've
donated to area economic development. We
sponsored the Manchester um Fourth of
July drone show um which was really
really uh county fairs, high school
district, state fairs and you know much
more. So we definitely want to get
involved and we want to give back and be
a community partner.
Uh but our ask is to just you know um
you know supporting ordinance that
allows for responsible data center
development in Cascade. Um, you know,
there's certainly a wide variety of ways
data centers can be built and I think
with the proposal that we're looking to
put forward and the, you know, ordinance
that we have asked to be put in place to
have clear, concise, enforcable rules so
that we can develop this responsibly.
Um, and it's a make it a win for
everybody involved. That's a lot we talk
about. It's a um, you know, win for
everybody involved with the community,
you know, and our company and so on so
forth. So, I think that is
it. Um, we want to be a good neighbor.
We want a fair ask, you know, um, we
want a fair look at the facts of the
situation. And, um, we'll get to Q&A
here. And, um, yeah, again, my email is
on the screen. So, for whatever reason
we don't get to one of your questions or
you have something that pops up tomorrow
next week, feel free to email and I'll
I'll get back to you anytime. I'm happy
to take anybody around our facility in
Manchester so you can get a sense of
what this hydro cooling facility looks
like. Again, that facility's been
operational for over a year now. I
haven't heard of a single single
complaint. That's a larger facility than
opposing here. So, thanks again
everybody for the time and organizing
this. Um and uh yeah, look forward to
>> Thanks Adam and Jeremy. So, we're moving
into the the the question and answer
period. the time where you can ask the
questions that are maybe weren't
answered if you had submitted. I know
there were quite a few questions that
were submitted on the online form and I
think Adam and Jeremy really tried to
get to them but certainly maybe in the
presentation today spur some more
questions for you. So um as we get going
here we've got got about an hour for
question and answer. We don't have to
take that much time but if you'd like to
take that much time we can. So you can
see on our handout that we offered that
we have asked you through this
conversation to be respectful to stay on
topic. I know that there's a lot of
information out there about data
centers, but we really want to talk
about this specific project that's being
proposed for Cascade. Um we ask you to
allow people to finish their thought
without interrupting them. Um we will
limit it the questions to one minute. So
instead of a um a filibuster like they
were doing in progress, right? So one
minute one minute per
questions um I'll be moderating this
discussion and and as always um let's
keep it keep it simple. So start out
here um who who would like to ask the
first question
always going to be one first.
>> I have several but a couple that could
be answered pretty quick. dB of the
generator. You have 50 dB generators.
Come on. What's actually
>> Yeah, great great question. So, our
generators are going to be in enclosures
and we would be committed to the um
deceler that would be first, you know,
such as 65 that even our generators when
they're operating would not be exceeding
the noise limit that's established at
that property line.
>> Okay, one more suggestion. Since
residents seem to be more alarmed than
most, you could move your building 200
ft to the west instead of you're
centering it on the property which moves
it closer to the reservation.
>> Yeah, I'd be open to that.
>> That's what our civil engineers came up
with based upon the photography, but I'd
be open to evaluating if that's a
combination that we can make shipments.
>> If this is approved and successful, will
we see more data centered ability to
build? No, it would be open to um
kind of like, you know, I'll use the
Cedar Rapids analogy that that I talked
about earlier. There there's not the
ability to go add, you know, far more
Google data centers into Cedar Rapids.
And it would be a similar situation
here. I'm not going to speak on behalf
of the utility company and their power
availability or anything like that. I
think that they're, you know, doing
proper planning,
but there's not the ability to just go
build, you know, a Google data center
right next door to us, um, with the
availability of the power. This is a
pretty small data center in the grand
scheme of things. So, I'd be open to
enforcements and restrictions that would
limit any ability to, you know, uh, for
us to expand or those things if that
makes sense.
>> And the last, uh, is there any, uh,
sales tax involved? Do you sell?
Of course you do. to make money. You
said is there sales tax as we know it
around here at all?
>> Yeah. So, um the way that our structure
would work just for clarity on how like
what our role is here is we are the um
developer of the building and it's kind
of standard how these facilities work.
We would just enter into a lease
agreement with with the tenant basically
that's going to run their computers and
and do whatever they want to do. Um so
just like any other commercial real
estate um those leases are not subject
to tax. Um, however, there could be
other taxable items. Um, you know, there
is state, just for clarity, there is
state tax incentives for um for data
centers that exist in Iowa. Um, I'm
trying to decide if it was a grocery
store or gas station, we would get sales
tax off of their revenue. Yep.
>> Will we get revenue off of this data
set? I don't I don't care what
>> No, it's fine. It's not a tax. No, not
for sales tax specifically. However,
there would be a um the like I mentioned
the the estimated value is about 400
million. There is also some state tax
exemptions for real property on the data
centers. Um and I don't have an exact
figure for you right now, but there
would be a m a very material amount
property tax base for this particular
facility. And there would be sales tax
in the future on electricity. There's a
time limit based upon when the facility
is built and then that time limit would
expire and then there would be sales tax
on the electricity in the future.
>> From a property tax standpoint, what
what would be the impact of that when
exist existing there on an annual basis
to debuke county debut schools casting
just you know if it's a $400 million
project
wise there's got to be a value there. So
do do they pay similar than a house or
Yeah, it would mean that would be
through the assessor and and they would
determine that value. Um, again, I don't
have an exact figure. It's going to be
less than 100% of our cost to build the
facility, but it's certainly going to be
more than um, you know, the taxable
value is going to be more than, you
know, 5 10% of the total cost there. So,
you you're I hate to throw out numbers
before the county assessor has done the
actual evaluation, but you're talking
about a property value that's in the
tens of millions of dollars. um from a
property tax standpoint and then just
for there would be sales tax in the
future when the there there's a time
limit um you know based upon the current
state where that that time limit expires
and then there is sales tax on the
electricity so there would be sales tax
in the future just not immediate.
>> Thank you. Yeah, good question.
You mentioned that the clos system
doesn't very much mention B on site but
there's no initial
good question there there is so it's a
it's a solution um that would actually
bring to the property we bring in in
totes um and it's the same sort of
solution that we Think think um think
like anifreeze in your car, right? Like
you need something to be able to cool
your engine and it needs to also be able
to survive the winter and not freeze and
turn into ice. So that is a product that
we would bring in. We would not be using
um water from Cascade to do the initial
fill. We would be bringing in this
outside liquid, fill it up, and then we
would expect that liquid to last a very
long time. And then for our specific
water usage that is just limited to
facilities, bathrooms, you know, maybe
some uh in the winter some
humidification of the building if it's
really drying and you know we need to do
that. Um and I would be open to a um you
know monthly restriction on water usage
for example. That would be I'd be very
open to that. excited to sign out
and there's different and I'm open to
you know requirements there as well
because there is different types of
fluids that you can get. For example,
the fluid that we use over at our
Manchester facility is a cornbased
biodegradable glycol solution that has
no you can the EPA has zero
requirements. You can spill 10,000
gallons of it and it's biodegrad. So
yeah, we definitely um
>> that's what that's what the ordinance
then. Yeah, we'll keep moving to it. I
mean, I'm we're open to these different
restrictions that are that are, you
know, common sense, but you know, we're
open to different restrictions that make
sense to accommodate any of these
concerns, right? We my goal is not to,
you know, tell you that we're going to
do closed loop and then don't magically
use 5 million gallons of water a day to
do that. We can put it right in the
ordinance that we have a, you know, a
restriction on water usage. It has to be
common sense. We need to be able to
flush the toilets, right? Um but we're
very open to um you know those types of
restrictions on those concerns. So
>> Okay. And I just have two more questions
before I take a seat. We talk you talked
about it being monitored. It's going to
monitor the compliance.
>> Yeah. So the state has some reporting
requirements that are monthly for data
centers and I so we'd be submitting
those reports for um all the different
requirements. So,
>> my last question would be that you said
that you're proud of what or you would
be proud of what the building looks
like.
>> I want you to know that I'm very proud
of what my house looks like right now
and the environment surrounding my house
right now.
>> Um, I'm concerned about the noise.
>> Um, I'm not sitting on my back porch and
hearing that noise. was concerned about
having my windows open in the evening to
sleep over the windows.
>> Um, so
>> no, absolutely. And and I think that you
know my my quick comments on that is I'
I'd be happy to bring you over to
Manchester and show you around that
particular facility, do a site tour so
you can kind of get a sense of what that
sound would be like because it's very
very quiet and um you know there's been
zero impact in a year now in Manchester
with any issues. We're actually closer
in Manchester residentially than we are
here. Um so it's um be happy to show you
just so you can get a sense because
sometimes it's hard unless you
physically felt it, seen it and touched
it, heard it. It's it's kind of hard to
get a sense there. Um and and and we
want to be good neighbors. If if if we
come in here and build this particular
facility and they're causing lots of
issues, violating the noise ordinance,
those sorts of things, it's going to
prohibit our business from growing in
the future. We have about a dozen
different operating facilities across
the state right now and you won't find a
single bad news article about our
business. Um, so yeah, we're very aware
and we want to one of our business core
values is neighborly. Coming here from
Iowa, being born in Iowa and trying to
grow this business, you know, being a
good neighbor is really, really
important. So yeah, thank you for the
questions.
>> I point out that and both of these
gentlemen because they deal with a lot
of electricity have meters on their
phone about how loud how loud, right? 50
50 or 65 dB is. And um earlier today and
then earlier this evening when you were
all talking to before we got started one
of them pulled out their phone and the
conversation just in this room was at 70
dB is so Adam is saying he's like it's
approximately 50 for there. So that's
some perspective. I know it's hard and
he had a chart up there but some
perspective of like normal conversation
was 70 dB and their facility runs
averaged at 50.
Interesting.
I just got a quick comment about maybe
John, but I mean difference though with
measuring conversation in a room or
measuring a car passing by or anything
all those sounds eventually stop
>> you know 50 dB out there doesn't stop
24-hour day 365 right that's the
difference though so I I there's been
medical research done at UCLA about the
effects of those drone sounds even low
volume droning sounds on people that are
working maybe working this around
facility versus people working in the
residential part. I would like to see
word about that versus
someone talking in a room versus this is
a a sound that does not stop.
>> Yeah, that's it's it's a good point,
right? It's a continuous sound and we're
not we're not disputing that and um I
think that's where you need to have the
limit that's put in place. Data centers
however and IO have been around for
decades, right? Like West De Mo for
example has some massive data centers
located extremely extremely close to
residential and they're expanding you
know all those data center facilities in
de mo altuna west and so on so forth has
Apple has a large data center that is
right next to residential none of those
facilities would have got approved if
they were causing issues and you would
hear about it in the news if if there
was issues there. So again, I would
invite anybody if they want to come take
a look at our Manchester facility that's
just down the road to get a sense of
what it is because if you get more than
a few hundred feet, then you can't even
really hear it. Um, which is, you know,
the whole purpose of the ordinance and
being in an industrial area having those
setbacks, those clear, you know,
defining restrictions. Um, because we we
would fundamentally not be building this
facility if it was going to cause, you
know, issues like that.
your original plan.
Okay. You also made a comment about, you
know, future expansion
or perhaps no future expansion.
Did I hear that correctly?
>> Uh, we have no future. Yeah, we have no
future expansion plans here. When I'm
talking about the future, I'm talking
about other locations and facilities
outside of Cascade. This is this is the
this is what we can do here and that's
it.
>> That being said
that's all I have.
So maybe some may after you get your
property gets it own and that be maybe
something in the future you may want to
sell off to another business not a data
there's a lot of
in my if I want to buy
>> you're saying um that we would sell the
excess land that we have nearby the
property um we
>> uh it's around 60,000 ft
>> how many square
20,000* 44. Yeah.
>> Yeah, I understand. There's a lot of
capacity.
>> Yeah, that's fuel.
But I just
>> um Yeah, that's that's never even
crossed my mind. Um um um I I think that
you know I guess if a business was
willing to purchase the land from us and
locate next to us in the industrial park
I guess and they were okay with that but
but there would be zero intention and
and honestly there's there's I would
anticipate in the ordinance there would
be some setback requirements that would
kind of limit any ability to sell land
because then that business is also going
to have setback requirements as well. So
you um no the buildable area and the
topography of this particular facility
is kind of it's kind of a hill is a nice
benefit because where we're located at
the bottom of this hill and and you know
as you go up the hill and you get into
the residential it's it's up and beyond
um you know so based upon the elevations
um you'll you'll barely even see the
roof of our building and we'll have it
screened right with an armor fence.
That's kind of our proposal there. Um,
but there would be no intention to sell
any of the land that we own right now
for anything else. And I think that'd be
a challenge with with the setback
requirements.
>> Where's the death measure?
>> Where do you measure that?
>> Oh, yeah. That 50 would be at our
property line. Um and and again that
would be kind of a similar level that
you would see in our Manchester
facility, but it's not 50 constant 24/7
365, but that's an average decel rating,
>> but it's not measured in the
subdivision.
>> No, no, no. Absolutely not. No, no.
That's that's at our property line.
We're looking for a clear enforcable
limit at our property line that we can
follow. We have this at many of our
other facilities and um you know we we
would not it would be a very very bad
investment in business for us to build
this facility with those enforcements in
place where we would risk you know our
investments if we were exceeding that
threshold. So um yeah good question
got it. Uh first of all the on the slide
you mentioned about jobs
for me if I'm in the wrong word you see
them create about 25 jobs.
>> Yeah.
>> Is that is that a fair characterization
of it?
>> Yes. I guess
how many of those would be at the
facility on a daily basis?
>> Um all 25 minus the people on their day
off you know um there would be 247 365
um on-site staff to operate this
facility. So yeah, I mean there's
there's minimums where we have to have
staff on site just to be able to operate
between the electrical, mechanical, you
know, all all those different sorts of
things. Site management, security. So
yeah, those are all physically located
at the facility 24/7 365.
So not all 25 are normal 7 days a week
off all you know three shifts for
example. But the other part of this
which is more of my but you only refer
to it as a data center. I have heard it
colloally referred to as an AI data
center. Is that a fair like my question
is do you have a potential lease
candidate?
>> We don't have a customer at this moment
in time. Um and it this is where like
the the data center structure is very
very short, right? Um this would be a
data center to you know plug in
computers to run AI technology. Yeah, it
it like the the cooling and all those
other requirements whether we're
plugging in storage or iPhone pictures
or those types of things. It you know
the the outside and all the other
I and I I understand it well enough. I
know that doesn't change kind of how
you're using it necessarily.
>> I'm concerned about it from an ethics
standpoint because I have ethical
concerns with AI. Um, and I think it's
fair to say that like iCloud storage
ethically is different than if it were
to be data data processing power for
flock something like that which has
plenty of and not to get into but has
experienced own issues with I'm sure
you're aware of that.
Was that a part of this conversation?
Well, I'm not going to probably touch on
the opening. Um,
>> but I think it's fair, but like you can,
you know, if you build a facility, you
can, you know, most use, but like if
there was a jeweler opening town
proposed where guidance, that would that
would be a fair concern.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I think I think
fundamentally AI is actually a function
of free speech. It's it's computer code.
It's a computer code at the end of the
day. And um I'm not saying that you know
probably it's not worth going down
through this particular discussion at
the end of the day the technology is
going to exist and it's important to
make sure that it exists responsibly
right and and that starts with the data
center that operates it. So um yes there
is there's definitely lots of compliance
you know um around
you know we have this in any business
you know um you can't you know
there's all those sorts of sorts of
things but um
>> yeah probably not going to go that's I
wasn't expecting to go deep into the but
that's just you know
>> one thing I forgot that I'd like to add
in it when you ask your question because
um we're a community. Would you please
state your name so Adam can have your
name to be able to respond to you
respectfully? So and I think gentlemen
I'm hearing and then sorry is
Dave.
>> Uh yeah questions but again regarding
the noise levels uh so you say 50dB now
I heard you kind of clarified that's
kind of typical noise level. Uh, and I
think more concerning is maybe the peak
noise levels. For instance, in
Manchester, it's very quiet to go there
in the winter. But I went there one day,
you know, on a hot day when the bands
are really running. I mean, and I went
really call it quiet, but it wasn't that
bad. But uh it was a little hard to get
a sense of the noise and because of the
west side of the building is I mean of
your facility in Manchester is but right
up against a long building so you can't
like go broadside to the facility and
and subs it. On the other side you got a
big field on the north side you have a
big substation between street and and so
forth. So, it's a little hard to get
sense, but one of the concerns here is
that u the east side of the property
line is only 400 ft from the property
line with the cold row of houses on M
Street and that close proximity is a
little bit concerning. Uh so like on a
hot day when maybe your fans are cranked
up uh and there's a westerly wind that
can carry noise and at night that's
probably the most concerning. uh you
know if you have a temperature inversion
the winter that tends to sort of noise
close to the ground and so forth. So
there may be some bombing cases where it
could be kind of disruptive.
um that that was and now if you look at
Manchester there's a farmhouse
there appears to be a farmhouse that's
about 400 ft away from your east
property across field but I look at the
parcel map it seems like most of the
residential stuff is is a lot further
away in Manchester than than 400 ft. So
that my only concern is that close
proximity and is the noise ever going to
be an issue?
>> No, that would mean that's where we're
looking to go with the clear enforceable
limits there at any point in time not
exceed 65. I'm not going to say it's
going to be 50 on the dot 24/7 through
65. You are correct that the cooling on
a hot day will be running a little bit
more. There's there's you know it's very
clear and obvious. Um but we would want
that limit um you know at the property
line. So that's very clear and forceful
that you know we are not going to exceed
that. Um and and again I think um you
know I don't know I don't know when you
took a trip over to to the Manchester
site um to to get to 65 at the property
line especially with the type of
setbacks that we're talking about here
would be would be extremely significant.
Um our our particular facility over in
Manchester
we have our equipment that is really
really close to the property line
actually much closer than what would be
here. that facility just for clarity
Manchester it's 50 megawatt so larger
than what we're closing here and it sits
on 6 acres of land not 15 and two so
this is a lot of additional space that
that noise will really start to fall off
quickly the um
sound level day and it was only uh write
it down but I think it says it was only
70 fb that was standing near the f right
next to that it's very close to the
property of the building so uh I can
understand maybe that's that's not well
hopefully it won't be a problem but
>> and that's what we're asking for right
we want to clear the door you know 65 dB
at the property line is really really
standard so the only comment I would
make and I don't know if we're comparing
apples to apples to that for instance in
Aurora Illinois um they had a lot of
people complaining about the noise made
by the data center there and they
negotiated with the this register they
negotiated with the city and they got it
uh we made an agreement of 55 dB during
the day and 45 dB at night. So my
question is is 6 and five dB reasonable
uh for uh considering the proximity to
the neighborhood because it's not just
dec
lot lot of data centers have setbacks uh
of an eighth of a mile or a quarter mile
here it's just that close proximity
point about the building in Manchester
and I think that that's what's really
nice about property the topography that
we have here is that we're sitting at
the bottom of the hill so the bottom of
the hill is actually going to be much
larger, you know, to block the sound
than the the building. That's
>> that will be great for blocking, I
think, higher pitch sounds, even lower
pitch sounds, they will refract around.
Um, and that's just the nature of
acoustics in but hopefully you won't
have that much low pitch sound but
that's it's not just how much sound you
have total but for instance a lot of
times when they measure in decibb they
use the c scale and that kind of thing
kind of looks more at the low end low
frequencies and those are the ones that
really harder to block with trees and so
forth with that they tend to penetrate
more and they're the ones that really
disturb it people
That's my boss.
>> I'm Andy Schneider and I live in Bulbury
and uh question I have is 65 decimals at
your property line. How far does the
sound actually go?
>> Yeah, you can't hear it. Yeah, this is
where I'd be happy to bring you out to
um you know, our Manchester facility and
and show you around there. After a
couple hundred feet, you can barely hear
it on a calm day. I mean, it's it's it's
pretty quiet. There's actually another
manufacturing company in Manchester, um
Strike Energy, not to throw them on the
bus, but if you're standing in front of
our driveway looking at our equipment,
you can actually hear their facility
over our equipment right in front of us.
So I I definitely hear the concern and
and you know understand that there are
nearby residents to the particular
facility. Um but you know talking about
the Manchester facility that particular
property line is a clear shot with with
with you know that farmhouse you had
mentioned um 400 ft with with no sorts
of you know uh hill or building to
stream at and and we've got zero zero
complaints um or from anybody else in
Cascade Ranch. Um and we have lots of
other facilities too as well where we're
um you know one particular community
that we had a facility up and going um
about six months ago. Um we are actually
getting questions on when we were going
to power up the facility for example. So
I completely understand the concern um
but we would want that clear enforceable
limit. um it's in an industrial park,
right? And and I understand that it does
but up next to an um you know
residential neighborhood, but whatever
those limits are um you know, we would
abide by it. So
you really don't know how far it goes.
You don't have any
modeling and and absolutely show that.
Yeah, that would be that would be
something that we could do. How far is
your facility to the closest
this particular property in Cascade? Um
to the nearest property length from
where our equipment's going to be, it's
probably 6 or 700 ft.
And then a common setback for
residential is 500 ft. So we would
exceed that.
Um, I'm Heather and I'm more concerned
about
nature, like the insects, the birds,
like how that affects pollinators
and migratory birds, migratory insects,
monarchs, bees, all of that kind of
stuff.
Will your decibb and the heat that gets
off and the light pollution from your
lights that you'll need at night for
your security and stuff, how will that
be affecting
light?
>> Yeah, that was a good question. It's a
common one that we get. Um, I'll adjust
the light version right away. This is
not going to be lit up like the fourth
of July. We would have screen, you know,
download just just for security purposes
at night. this thing does not will not
be able to like the boards that I should
probably make that and um um yeah I
think that our goal there is to you know
minimize all of those things as much as
possible fundamentally there's lots of
businesses that exist in industrial
parks and you know they have equipment
running 24/7 365 um and you know in lots
of different areas in Iowa this is a
common business so we would follow all
of the standard protocols part of that
comes with the lead certification right
the lead certification is not only from
you know the operations of the building
but it's also from the design and the
construction process. So there's
definitely requirements there that we'd
be following to to do that.
>> Would you be putting like the trees the
tree that you have in the back be doing
more like native trees for that or
>> um I don't think we have a specific um
you know set of trees picked out at this
point in time, but we're we're we're
flexible there on what whatever makes
the most sense aesthetically and you
know locally, environmentally, all those
sorts of things.
My name is Sheila and I live on Malberry
Drive and my back door would be a stone
throw to where your building is going to
go.
And like you said, with this noise,
animals have a better hearing than we
do. So maybe if they can get of of the
veterinarian to let us know if it's
going to affect on any of the animals on
our street and we have a lot of dogs and
cats.
So that is one of the main problems I am
thinking of.
Plus, if there's anybody that has
epilepsy or any of the children,
will that cause seizures?
Or have you gone into any of the medical
things about how that noise is going to
affect the human body?
I'm not worried about the view. I'm
worried about my neighbors.
>> They're like family.
And I don't understand why this building
has to be so close to where we all live
with our children.
Why couldn't it be further out into
another area where there is no
residential houses?
It makes no sense to me.
And if there is any underlying
uh motive of money or takebacks or
anything that is involved with anybody
in the in the political or money in
Cascade,
well, even though you're shaking your
head, no. Uh it's politics.
It all comes down to politics.
So I would I would go forward with this
if it were on outskirts and in the
middle of nowhere.
>> So um understand your concern. Um and I
think overall Cascade and you know
working with the different leadership of
the community has done a really great
job of you know putting on an event like
this right so that we can have these
conversations. Um
there's a lot of questions there. I
think I think what I'll touch on is
again these particular facilities um
have been around for a very very long
time especially here and um none of
those concerns um
are are an issue with any of these
particular locations across Iowa um and
you have them located like I said near
residential investing near residential
in Altuna there there's lots of
different block he for example um Apple
has a 2,000 acre facility that they're
developing right you don't have to walk
to your next special. Um,
I don't know if I'm being able to give
you all the answers to all your
questions, but we're really trying to do
this responsibly. Um, you know, I am
from just down the road in smalltown,
Iowa, and we're not trying to come in
here and ram this thing through. We're
really here to have an open conversation
to hear the concerns, ask the city of
Cascade to put in restrictions so that
we can operate. We're one of the only
businesses that would have to come in
and have, you know, a conversation like
this to be able to just do our business
and operate. But we're willing to do it
and we have done it and we have lots of
different facilities operating and and
our reputation and our credibility means
everything to us. We wouldn't be where
we are here today having this
conversation if we were causing all
these different issues in different
communities where we've already been
established. So, um, yeah. So, how many
data centers do we have in Iowa compared
to other students?
>> Um, I don't have an exact figure for
you, but I can give it to you.
>> We have a lot.
>> Yes, we have a lot. Yes. Yes. There's a
this is um this is a very active um
industry that that has, you know,
there's um there's some information out
there um on, you know, how many jobs and
the billions that it brings into the
economy of Iowa. Maybe'll touch on that.
um gas spot location and why does it
have to be right here? Um for for a few
different reasons. It's located near
power where infrastructure exists and
it's it's not easy to just bring power
to the middle of nowhere, right? So
that's that's number one. It's located
near the power um and it's an industrial
park. There's fiber nearby. Fiber is a
requirement and you know Cascade and
then here in Iowa we have a really
robust fiber network. So part of why,
you know, a lot of this activity is
taking place in Iowa is because we have
all the key ingredients to be able to do
this type of business. And and I think
it's a great opportunity um you know to
bring additional jobs, construction,
long-term employment, a tax base to all
these different communities in Iowa.
That's that's kind of my thing.
>> How professional are your workers going
to be? I we'd be happy to show you our
facility in Cedar Falls. We our again
our reputation and credibility means
everything to us. I think we have a we
have a pretty nice facility over in
Manchester and they'd be happy to take
you to show you around our main
headquarters in Cedar Falls. Um but
yeah, very very professional.
>> Who's going to train the ones for Cats?
>> Who's going to train?
>> Who's going to train the people that are
going to be working here in Cat State?
>> Yeah, we have um so we have um his name
is John Sasser. He's our director of
data centers. He has about 23 years of
experience and um he's been in he
started you know all the way at the
ground level in operations and has gone
all the way through up through most
recently before we hired him he was a
chief technology officer at the company.
So he's extremely um experienced in this
particular industry and we have um we're
we're a team of about 80 um right now
and we have lots of different you know
directors and in managers to to you know
train employees um on-site operations
electrical mechanical those sorts of
things.
>> So I'd like to see
>> I'm going to let somebody else have a
here for a minute. Okay. And then you
can hold your thought back to winter
time. Okay.
>> Who else would like to ask a question?
Thank you. I'm
property joining the industrial.
>> Um I'm just curious, can you comment on
how it went from the Bitcoin to Yeah.
>> Yeah. No question. So um that's just
where there's been a significant shift
in the industry. We've seen a lot of
other Bitcoin mining companies that have
shifted to this opportunity because
there is just such a significant demand.
Um and and if you look at back to my
kind of earlier comments, the core
principles of what we were doing was we
were building infrastructure to run
computers. Um Bitcoin miners are just
computers and they run 24/7. It was a
data center, right? What we have over in
Manchester is a data center. Um this is
just a different type of data center,
right? Um,
you know, that's that's kind of how the
the the market is demanding this um, you
know, and we're in a good position with
based upon our experience to be able to
execute and deliver on um, you know,
this demand. So, we still are building
out other facilities. We have a facility
we're building in South Dakota for
Bitcoin Mines. We're expanding further.
Um, but this is a, you know, an
opportunity with this particular
property where we have access to the
fiber and and the sorts of things that
we need to be able to do this particular
project. Hopefully that answers your
question. Thank you.
Yeah. needed on your tiny durable
requests. One of them, the first one was
uh the design documentation architecture
in this CMD
and it can any kind of topographic
information on your network your network
I should say. This is this is submitted
on the right question. Is that right?
>> Okay. Yeah. Um so all of the
documentation we have on the engineer is
just preliminary. Um the design and
engineering for this particular facility
would take place once once we have
approval. It's u millions of dollars to
do the design and engineering for this
particular facility. Um and um you know
civil engine
I can glide beyond. So the idea of
putting this together and you're not
using kind of configuration management
maybe you don't have any kind of
graphic.
>> Yeah, this this is it's a little it's a
little blurry but this is from
fairground engineer. Um this is a
>> that's a lot I'm talking about what's
inside.
>> Yeah. Do you have any subets? Do you are
using a DMC? How are you doing this
servers? Yeah, a lot of that would be,
you know, proprietary business somehow
that would be done.
>> I want you to pop the hood. So, it seems
like
>> Yeah. And if you were a customer in the
data center, that that would be the
case, right? Like we would engage with
our customer um you know, as they're
bringing in their computers to be able
to run and all those sorts of things. Um
what I what I can assure you is we would
work with, you know, to make sure we
meet all the building codes and this
goes into the lead certification. The
lead certification is not an easy um you
know certification to meet. It's pretty
rigorous. It's additional cost. It's
through the design, the construction and
the operations of the particular
facility. Um
>> are you going to follow ITIL 4IL version
5?
>> I am not an engineer. Guys, I can assure
you that you know built into these
different standards meaning all the
local state codes from a building code
perspective we
stand on project management too. I still
manage.
It has nothing to do with talking about
nothing with this portion you're talking
about after the customer.
Wait, I I have a couple more questions.
One recip
I also ask for disaster recovery
business continuous uh continuation type
uh plan.
>> Yeah. Yeah. uh emergency action plan is
pretty um you know common with some
different you know communities that we
work with. So um we regularly engage
with police, fire, you know emergency
management, those types of things. So
we'd be open to that as a requirement of
the ordinance to have some sort of
required emergency action plan single
bullet point instead generators. Are you
using high availability? Are you
mirroring somewhere? How are you doing
SAS recovery? If we have an S3 tornado
come through here and take down three or
four substations, if you're down for 120
hours, you're going to run the
generators for 120 hours in a
residential neighborhood next door.
>> There there's limitations on that
through the state. It's a state air
permitted process for the generators.
So, there's a limitation on how many you
could run.
>> But the generators are here for disaster
recovery.
>> They are backup. Yeah, the generators
are there for backup. And you know um
luckily here in the United States we
have very very good reliability on the
utility grid which is something that you
know um I'm very fortunate for but we do
have these backup generators just in
case.
>> Yeah I guess
um other than extremely different less
than 24 hours. The other two questions I
have is one you said you're not using
waterbased what fluid in your cooling
systems. No, it is based. Yeah. Yeah. My
concern there is in the event this
project doesn't work, would you be
willing to put together a shy bond so
that we don't have to carry the cost of
the clean out afterwards?
>> Yeah, I think that we'd be open to that.
Um there's a lot of what I will say as a
as a counter to that is there's a lot of
other businesses that build a lot of
other things and have a lot of other
accessory equipment um to their business
that they are not having to guarantee if
they go out of business for example. So,
you're asking about the businesses. I'm
asking about this project's potential
>> and you're saying you're open to which
things.
>> Finally, as far as we go with the
residential neighborhood here, uh, is
there any compensation for property
values dropping?
>> We haven't seen property values drop
around any data center. So, no, we would
not be looking into doing that. Sure.
>> Sorry. I think that that is a
conversation that probably really needs
to happen with county officials more
than the developer of the project. So,
here
>> I just wanted to know if there are any
state or federal or city funds involved
in this and if you plan to apply for it.
>> Good question. So um the only um there's
no funds there's sales tax exemption
uh from the state for data science that
has been around for a very very long
time. Um that would be the only type of
incentives that we would be seeking. We
would not be seeking any other local
incentives any other federal incentives.
It it would simply just be the state
exemptions on sales tax um and use tax
that already exist. So good question.
>> I don't know the exact number but a lot
of people more than 20 you should know.
>> Yes. Yes. More than 20. It's it's it's
you know several gigawatts of
operational um there's uh again there's
lots of facilities all over Iowa. So I
don't have the exact specific number for
you. Um and I don't even know if you
could get the exact specific number but
yeah there's lots of lots of data
centers in Iowa. There's lots of data
centers that are building in Iowa such
as overs
generators.
>> Uh we're planning for diesel diesel.
>> Diesel. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um only backup situations and um
you know periodic testing.
>> Yeah. Y
Thank you so much. Uh the
jobs are available
to
$18 $24 an hour for technician in Cedar
Falls 18 to 25 mills 18 to 25 and Little
Cedar Sage I I always figure 5 weeks
times $40 is $2,000.
So that basically the top would be
somewhere in $50,000
would be two jobs would be doing 75 to
80,000 I mean that's quite distracting.
Yeah. So the 75 to 80 would be on bridge
and these are going to be um for example
uh an introductory on-site technician
that's doing very very basic repairs is
going to be very different from an
electrician from a site manager from a
mechanical on this advanced equipment.
Um those particular facilities are um uh
they're much lower overall investment to
build. This is a $400 million facility
that has a lot more um you know
sophistication to it. requires a higher
level of talent to operate the facility.
So yeah, those are those are the
positions the entry level
is like we're hiring a high school
facilities to do unplugged machines and
plug them back in. That's a very
entrylevel position versus a you know I
think we all know electricians are
getting paid these days. Um so yeah that
that
>> 25 that's called 50,000.
>> Yeah and that's that's that's on
75.
>> Yeah. So there'll be a little bit of
spread there, right? There'll be
there'll be positions that are over six
figures in this particular facility and
there'll be positions that are 50,000.
uh mention certification. What level do
you typically give? Um typically the
minimum lead certification is what we
would be targeting here. So
um had a question I just
thank you. Um
sorry I was really asking the question
but I feel very um why do you have the
map on the on the board over there? Um
you mentioned that it's going to go into
the center part. Um and I think someone
over here mentioned perhaps it will be a
consideration to move further
side of
>> the other way so that it gives you a gap
between the
list. Yep. This was just um this is the
the the first draft from our civil
engineers based upon topography and kind
of how they need to make work and with
maybe some assumptions on some setbacks,
but I think um as long as we're
physically able to do it, which I don't
see any issues why we would be able to
shift it a little bit to the west, I
think that we would be open to that. Um
and we could probably work with the city
of Cascade to have maybe a reduction in
the setback requirement off of um the
the west road here
south.
mining center in Manchester. So, it's
not a data center, it's mining center.
It's a data center. Um there there's
just different there's different tiers
of data centers. They're typically
referred to as tiers one through a tier
five and that has to do with the level
of redundancy and backup. Um if there
was a power outage or you know a piece
of equipment fails, um mining data
centers has a very very low level of
redundancy. So there's no backup if you
know um a piece of equipment were to
fail or the power to go out for example.
But fundamentally it is a data center.
It's um has computers running 24/7 and
then you know um that particular
facility is a liquid cooled facility. So
in in the open core it's it's extremely
similar to what we would be building
here. What we're building here just has
a higher level of redundancy to make
sure that the equipment doesn't go down.
And you mentioned that there
reslaints
normally from a residence.
>> Yes.
>> By someone was a farmed. Is that is that
resident
vacant or is someone actually living
there?
>> I read certain someone lives there
because I've I remember having a
conversation that was an initial concern
with Manchester. I believe was with that
resident that lived there. They were
concerned that it could be an issue. So
I believe that there is a resident
there, but I I I couldn't tell you my
>> understanding that it's actually
right now,
but that's just my own.
>> Yeah, my name is Joe.
Just to clarify, I hope they recognize
what I saw in this side smaller than it
is
so that when people do take up
invitation I can do they'll see the same
thing that you're this is one capability
correct with yard one I can read because
that's a preliminary drawing that can't
so you can possibly answer all the
question
so that's a preliminary drawing
>> yeah I can answer both what I've seen
there is
different and what I see in Manchester
are still so people understand that when
you go up there it's not going to look
like one and that's okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Is that a correct?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, so there is one building
here and and then we would have the
cooling adjacent to the building. Um,
the Manchester facility to describe it
very simply as a bunch of small modules
and then the cooling is around the
entire property if you will. So, um, I
think the key points to make there is
the cooling capacity is still the it's
actually greater in Manchester because
it's a larger overall facility. Um, and
uh, it's a much smaller facility. It's
about 6 acres that we have there versus
15 acres here. So, um, think about if
you've been in a facility, think about,
um, if you put all of those, um, you
know, containers where the equipment is
running all in the center and then you
get all the cooling equipment
surrounding it. It's it's it's
pretty similar overall from from the
the, you know, core. Yeah.
>> I think we we probably have time for two
to three more questions. So, is there
anyone who hasn't asked a question yet
that I'd like to get to before we wrap
up? Thank you for being here. I can take
this um a lot of concern, I think,
around the generator um issue and
operating. It's noisy.
>> Can you help us understand how often we
can expect that the generators are
actually running? And I do think that,
you know, if the system goes down and
they're running non-stop, that's we hear
a lot about that as a concern. I think
it is a concern but um talk about what
we can expect. How often how many
generators and how often
would they be?
>> Yeah, good good question. So um the the
maybe the first really important point
to make is that the generators are in
enclosures. So the enclosure is a
self-explanatory, but it encloses the
entire generator which greatly reduces
the overall sound. And that ties back to
whether it's a generator or a dry cooler
or any other piece of equipment that's
making noise at the property. We want to
have a very enforcable, you know, level
at that property line to to make sure
that we're not going to violate it um
and and whatnot. So um periodic testing,
you know, just for backup.
>> Um I can't tell you definitively at this
point in time. Um but you know certainly
not on a daily basis if that if that's
what you're wondering. Um and um
yeah the so in enclosure um again
there's an air permit that we have to
acquire. There's certain um efficiency
of that equipment that we have to have.
There's an empty rating. So um yeah but
diesel generators are common backup
generation method at every single data
center. So we would be following you
know the standards there. So
>> each
>> um based upon this particular facility
um without having exact number for you
right now maybe around 15.
>> Yes.
>> What's your timeline look like? This is
very very bare bones plan. Yeah. When
when would you expect to have permit
drawings?
>> Um yeah, good question. So, um we would
expect this is a long process, right?
It's a it's a pretty substantial build.
Um
depending on, you know, when approval, I
would expect that this process would be
around 12 to 18 months from the time
that we have the ability to move forward
to the time that it's, you know,
operational. So, it's a it's it's a it's
a long construction process.
Just how tall is the highest building?
>> Um I think the eve is uh the sidewalls
are 22 ft. The eve is somewhere around
26 28 something like that.
>> 25 and 31 20 25
you know.
understand you can't give a definitive
answer, but I don't think it was
remotely close to being definitive about
what the word periodically does.
>> So, you said certainly not every day,
which I would certainly work on every
day, but every other day is still the
one testing and what's periodically.
>> Yeah. Um, I think you would expect
depending on the my expertise is like in
the the maintenance of the data centers,
I can get back to you on that question
and anybody else who has that question.
If you want to send me my emails not up
there, I can let you know what that
would look like. Um, I don't want to
make any assumptions because my
experience and expertise is not in the
maintenance of the data centers. Um but
yeah, if you want to send me an email, I
will absolutely get back to, you know,
you and anybody else who has that
particular question on what the
expected, you know, testing would be.
So,
one last question. Will anybody on Hill?
Absolutely.
>> It's weird because
When my doors are open on my deck, my
back door is right there and I can hear
the construction building. I can hear
them working in there. So, how can you
tell say that I'm not going to be able
to hear 15 generators?
>> Yeah, I would. That's why we're looking
to have the cleared enforceable vessel
limit. um because that that will allow
us to make sure that we're meeting, you
know, those expectations of the city and
and I mean this is um um
yeah, we just want that clear and
enforceable rule. So um there there's
been plenty of um data centers that
operate across the state and near
residential and you know we would be um
happy to make sure we're meeting
exceeding those requirements. So
>> we have one following
up question. So you have no idea how
authentic.
A lot of good questions and I learned a
lot tonight and I hope you did as well.
think you know that this is an ongoing
discussion and um I know Adam maybe you
can talk about the next steps and we'll
wrap up this application.
>> Yeah. No, thank you again everyone for
the time tonight. We definitely
appreciate the the questions and and
hearing more about our projects and and
our goal here is to build um like we
talked about a responsible data center
where we're asking for cleaning
enforcement rules and um you know we we
look forward to continuing the
discussion. So appreciate everybody's
time. My contact information is great
here. happy to answer any email
questions if there's anything that comes
up. Happy to give a tour of our
facilities uh in Manchester and students
any time. So appreciate uh appreciate
everybody making time to to discuss
project.
Thanks. It's not affect